<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (C) 2006-2023 Oracle and/or its affiliates.

    This file is part of VirtualBox base platform packages, as
    available from https://www.virtualbox.org.

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation, in version 3 of the
    License.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
    WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
    General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, see <https://www.gnu.org/licenses>.

    SPDX-License-Identifier: GPL-3.0-only
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<appendix id="privacy">

  <title>&product-name; Privacy Information</title>

  <para>
    Version 5, Dec 13, 2012
  </para>

  <para>
    The Oracle Privacy Policies posted on
    <ulink url="https://www.oracle.com/legal/privacy/privacy-policy.html" />
    apply to your personal data collected and used by Oracle. The
    following privacy information describes in more detail which
    information is exchanged between the &product-name; application and
    Oracle, and which information is collected by the virtualbox.org
    website.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 1 virtualbox.org.</emphasis> The
    "virtualbox.org" website logs anonymous usage information such as
    your IP address, geographical location, browser type, referral
    source, length of visit and number of page views while you visit
    (collectively, "anonymous data"). In addition, but only if you
    choose to register, the website's bug tracking and forum services
    store the data you choose to reveal upon registration, such as your
    user name and contact information.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 2 Cookies.</emphasis> The virtualbox.org
    website, the bug tracker and the forum services use cookies to
    identify and track the visiting web browser and, if you have
    registered, to facilitate login. Most browsers allow you to refuse
    to accept cookies. While you can still visit the website with
    cookies disabled, logging into the bug tracker and forum services
    will most likely not work without them.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 3 &product-name; registration
    process.</emphasis> The &product-name; application may ask that the
    user optionally register with Oracle. If you choose to register,
    your name, e-mail address, country and company will be submitted to
    Oracle and stored together with the IP address of the submitter as
    well as product version and platform being used.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 4 Update notifications.</emphasis> The
    &product-name; application may contact Oracle to find out whether a
    new version of &product-name; has been released and notify the user
    if that is the case. In the process, anonymous data such as your IP
    address and a non-identifying counter, together with the product
    version and the platform being used, is sent so that the server can
    find out whether an update is available. By default, this check is
    performed once a day. You change this interval or disable these
    checks altogether in the &product-name; preferences.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 5 Usage of personal information.</emphasis>
    Oracle may use anonymous and personal data collected by the means
    above for statistical purposes as well as to automatically inform
    you about new notices related to your posts on the bug tracker and
    forum services, to administer the website and to contact you due to
    technical issues. Oracle may also inform you about new product
    releases related to &product-name;.
  </para>

  <para>
    In no event will personal data without your express consent be
    provided to any third parties, unless Oracle may be required to do
    so by law or in connection with legal proceedings.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">§ 6 Updates.</emphasis> Oracle may update the
    privacy policy at any time by posting a new version at
    <ulink url="https://www.oracle.com/legal/privacy/privacy-policy.html" />
    and the privacy information will be kept up to date in the
    documentation which comes with the &product-name; application. You
    should check these places occasionally to ensure you are happy with
    any changes.
  </para>

</appendix>
