<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright (C) 2006-2023 Oracle and/or its affiliates.

    This file is part of VirtualBox base platform packages, as
    available from https://www.virtualbox.org.

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation, in version 3 of the
    License.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
    WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
    General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, see <https://www.gnu.org/licenses>.

    SPDX-License-Identifier: GPL-3.0-only
-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<chapter id="TechnicalBackground">

  <title>Technical Background</title>

  <para>
    This chapter provides additional information for readers who are
    familiar with computer architecture and technology and wish to find
    out more about how &product-name; works <emphasis>under the
    hood</emphasis>. The contents of this chapter are not required
    reading in order to use &product-name; successfully.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="vboxconfigdata">

    <title>Where &product-name; Stores its Files</title>

    <para>
      In &product-name;, a virtual machine and its settings are
      described in a virtual machine settings file in XML format. In
      addition, most virtual machines have one or more virtual hard
      disks. These are typically represented by disk images, such as
      those in VDI format. The location of these files may vary,
      depending on the host operating system. See
      <xref linkend="vboxconfigdata-machine-folder"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Global configuration data for &product-name; is maintained in
      another location on the host. See
      <xref linkend="vboxconfigdata-global"/>.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="vboxconfigdata-machine-folder">

      <title>The Machine Folder</title>

      <para>
        By default, each virtual machine has a directory on your host
        computer where all the files of that machine are stored: the XML
        settings file, with a <filename>.vbox</filename> file extension,
        and its disk images. This is called the <emphasis>machine
        folder</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>
        By default, this machine folder is located in a common folder
        called <filename>VirtualBox VMs</filename>, which &product-name;
        creates in the current system user's home directory. The
        location of this home directory depends on the conventions of
        the host operating system, as follows:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Windows, this is the location returned by the
            <literal>SHGetFolderPath</literal> function of the Windows
            system library Shell32.dll, asking for the user profile. A
            typical location is
            <filename>C:\Users\<replaceable>username</replaceable></filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Linux, macOS, and Oracle Solaris, this is generally
            taken from the environment variable
            <filename>$HOME</filename>, except for the user
            <literal>root</literal> where it is taken from the account
            database. This is a workaround for the frequent trouble
            caused by users using &product-name; in combination with the
            tool <command>sudo</command>, which by default does not
            reset the environment variable <filename>$HOME</filename>.
          </para>

          <para>
            A typical location on Linux and Oracle Solaris is
            <filename>/home/<replaceable>username</replaceable></filename>
            and on macOS is
            <filename>/Users/<replaceable>username</replaceable></filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        For simplicity, we abbreviate the location of the home directory
        as <filename>$HOME</filename>. Using that convention, the common
        folder for all virtual machines is <filename>$HOME/VirtualBox
        VMs</filename>.
      </para>

      <para>
        As an example, when you create a virtual machine called "Example
        VM", &product-name; creates the following:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            A machine folder: <filename>$HOME/VirtualBox VMs/Example
            VM/</filename>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the machine folder, a settings file: <filename>Example
            VM.vbox</filename>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the machine folder, a virtual disk image:
            <filename>Example VM.vdi</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        This is the default layout if you use the
        <emphasis role="bold">Create New Virtual Machine</emphasis>
        wizard described in <xref linkend="create-vm-wizard" />. Once you
        start working with the VM, additional files are added. Log files
        are in a subfolder called <filename>Logs</filename>, and if you
        have taken snapshots, they are in a
        <filename>Snapshots</filename> subfolder. For each VM, you can
        change the location of its snapshots folder in the VM settings.
      </para>

      <para>
        You can change the default machine folder by selecting
        <emphasis role="bold">Preferences</emphasis> from the
        <emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu in the &product-name;
        main window. Then, in the displayed window, click on the
        <emphasis role="bold">General</emphasis> tab. Alternatively, use
        the <command>VBoxManage setproperty machinefolder</command>
        command. See <xref linkend="vboxmanage-setproperty" />.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="vboxconfigdata-global">

      <title>Global Settings</title>

      <para>
        In addition to the files for the virtual machines,
        &product-name; maintains global configuration data in the
        following directory:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Linux and Oracle Solaris:</emphasis>
            <filename>$HOME/.config/VirtualBox</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Windows:</emphasis>
            <filename>$HOME/.VirtualBox</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">macOS:</emphasis>
            <filename>$HOME/Library/VirtualBox</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        &product-name; creates this configuration directory
        automatically, if necessary. You can specify an alternate
        configuration directory by either setting the
        <literal>VBOX_USER_HOME</literal> environment variable, or on
        Linux or Oracle Solaris by using the standard
        <literal>XDG_CONFIG_HOME</literal> variable. Since the global
        <filename>VirtualBox.xml</filename> settings file points to all
        other configuration files, this enables switching between
        several &product-name; configurations.
      </para>

      <para>
        In this configuration directory, &product-name; stores its
        global settings file, an XML file called
        <filename>VirtualBox.xml</filename>. This file includes global
        configuration options and a list of registered virtual machines
        with pointers to their XML settings files.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="vboxconfigdata-summary-locations">

      <title>Summary of Configuration Data Locations</title>

      <para>
        The following table gives a brief overview of the configuration
        data locations on an &product-name; host.
      </para>

      <table id="table-config-summary" tabstyle="oracle-all">
        <title>Configuration File Locations</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Setting</emphasis>
                </para></entry>
              <entry><para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Location</emphasis>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>
                  Default machines folder
                </para></entry>
              <entry><para>
                  <filename>$HOME/VirtualBox VMs</filename>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><para>
                  Default disk image location
                </para></entry>
              <entry><para>
                  In each machine's folder
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><para>
                  Machine settings file extension
                </para></entry>
              <entry><para>
                  <filename>.vbox</filename>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><para>
                  Media registry
                </para></entry>
              <entry><para>
                  Each machine settings file
                </para>



                <para>
                  Media registration is done automatically when a
                  storage medium is attached to a VM
                </para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="vboxconfigdata-XML-files">

      <title>&product-name; XML Files</title>

      <para>
        &product-name; uses XML for both the machine settings files and
        the global configuration file,
        <filename>VirtualBox.xml</filename>.
      </para>

      <para>
        All &product-name; XML files are versioned. When a new settings
        file is created, for example because a new virtual machine is
        created, &product-name; automatically uses the settings format
        of the current &product-name; version. These files may not be
        readable if you downgrade to an earlier version of
        &product-name;. However, when &product-name; encounters a
        settings file from an earlier version, such as after upgrading
        &product-name;, it attempts to preserve the settings format as
        much as possible. It will only silently upgrade the settings
        format if the current settings cannot be expressed in the old
        format, for example because you enabled a feature that was not
        present in an earlier version of &product-name;.
      </para>

      <para>
        In such cases, &product-name; backs up the old settings file in
        the virtual machine's configuration directory. If you need to go
        back to the earlier version of &product-name;, then you will
        need to manually copy these backup files back.
      </para>

      <para>
        We intentionally do not document the specifications of the
        &product-name; XML files, as we must reserve the right to modify
        them in the future. We therefore strongly suggest that you do
        not edit these files manually. &product-name; provides complete
        access to its configuration data through its the
        <command>VBoxManage</command> command line tool, see
        <xref linkend="vboxmanage" /> and its API, see
        <xref linkend="VirtualBoxAPI" />.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="technical-components">

    <title>&product-name; Executables and Components</title>

    <para>
      &product-name; was designed to be modular and flexible. When the
      &product-name; graphical user interface (GUI) is opened and a VM
      is started, at least the following three processes are running:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>VBoxSVC</command>, the &product-name; service process
          which always runs in the background. This process is started
          automatically by the first &product-name; client process and
          exits a short time after the last client exits. The first
          &product-name; service can be &vbox-mgr;,
          <command>VBoxManage</command>,
          <command>VBoxHeadless</command>, the web service amongst
          others. The service is responsible for bookkeeping,
          maintaining the state of all VMs, and for providing
          communication between &product-name; components. This
          communication is implemented using COM/XPCOM.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            When we refer to <emphasis>clients</emphasis> here, we mean
            the local clients of a particular <command>VBoxSVC</command>
            server process, not clients in a network. &product-name;
            employs its own client/server design to allow its processes
            to cooperate, but all these processes run under the same
            user account on the host operating system, and this is
            totally transparent to the user.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The GUI process, <command>VirtualBoxVM</command>, a client
          application based on the cross-platform Qt library. When
          started without the <option>--startvm</option> option, this
          application acts as &vbox-mgr;, displaying the VMs and their
          settings. It then communicates settings and state changes to
          <command>VBoxSVC</command> and also reflects changes effected
          through other means, such as the <command>VBoxManage</command>
          command.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the <command>VirtualBoxVM</command> client application is
          started with the <option>--startvm</option> argument, it loads
          the VMM library which includes the actual hypervisor and then
          runs a virtual machine and provides the input and output for
          the guest.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Any &product-name; front-end, or client, will communicate with the
      service process and can both control and reflect the current
      state. For example, either the VM selector or the VM window or
      VBoxManage can be used to pause the running VM, and other
      components will always reflect the changed state.
    </para>

    <para>
      The &product-name; GUI application, called &vbox-mgr;, is only one
      of several available front ends, or clients. The complete list
      shipped with &product-name; is as follows:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>VirtualBoxVM</command>: The Qt front end implementing
          &vbox-mgr; and running VMs.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>VBoxManage</command>: A less user-friendly but more
          powerful alternative. See <xref linkend="vboxmanage" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>VBoxHeadless</command>: A VM front end which does not
          directly provide any video output and keyboard or mouse input,
          but enables redirection through the VirtualBox Remote Desktop
          Extension. See <xref linkend="vboxheadless" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <command>vboxwebsrv</command>: The &product-name; web service
          process which enables control of an &product-name; host
          remotely. This is described in detail in the &product-name;
          Software Development Kit (SDK) reference. See
          <xref linkend="VirtualBoxAPI" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The &product-name; Python shell: A Python alternative to
          <command>VBoxManage</command>. This is also described in the
          SDK reference.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Internally, &product-name; consists of many more or less separate
      components. You may encounter these when analyzing &product-name;
      internal error messages or log files. These include the following:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          IPRT: A portable runtime library which abstracts file access,
          threading, and string manipulation. Whenever &product-name;
          accesses host operating features, it does so through this
          library for cross-platform portability.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VMM (Virtual Machine Monitor): The heart of the hypervisor.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          EM (Execution Manager): Controls execution of guest code.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          TRPM (Trap Manager): Intercepts and processes guest traps and
          exceptions.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          HM (Hardware Acceleration Manager): Provides support for VT-x
          and AMD-V.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GIM (Guest Interface Manager): Provides support for various
          paravirtualization interfaces to the guest.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          PDM (Pluggable Device Manager): An abstract interface between
          the VMM and emulated devices which separates device
          implementations from VMM internals and makes it easy to add
          new emulated devices. Through PDM, third-party developers can
          add new virtual devices to &product-name; without having to
          change &product-name; itself.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          PGM (Page Manager): A component that controls guest paging.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          TM (Time Manager): Handles timers and all aspects of time
          inside guests.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          CFGM (Configuration Manager): Provides a tree structure which
          holds configuration settings for the VM and all emulated
          devices.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          SSM (Saved State Manager): Saves and loads VM state.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VUSB (Virtual USB): A USB layer which separates emulated USB
          controllers from the controllers on the host and from USB
          devices. This component also enables remote USB.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          DBGF (Debug Facility): A built-in VM debugger.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          &product-name; emulates a number of devices to provide the
          hardware environment that various guests need. Most of these
          are standard devices found in many PC compatible machines and
          widely supported by guest operating systems. For network and
          storage devices in particular, there are several options for
          the emulated devices to access the underlying hardware. These
          devices are managed by PDM.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Guest Additions for various guest operating systems. This is
          code that is installed from within a virtual machine. See
          <xref linkend="guestadditions" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The "Main" component is special. It ties all the above bits
          together and is the only public API that &product-name;
          provides. All the client processes listed above use only this
          API and never access the hypervisor components directly. As a
          result, third-party applications that use the &product-name;
          Main API can rely on the fact that it is always well-tested
          and that all capabilities of &product-name; are fully exposed.
          It is this API that is described in the &product-name; SDK.
          See <xref linkend="VirtualBoxAPI" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hwvirt">

    <title>Hardware Virtualization</title>

    <para>
      &product-name; enables software in the virtual machine to run
      directly on the processor of the host, but an array of complex
      techniques is employed to intercept operations that would
      interfere with your host. Whenever the guest attempts to do
      something that could be harmful to your computer and its data,
      &product-name; steps in and takes action. In particular, for lots
      of hardware that the guest believes to be accessing,
      &product-name; simulates a certain <emphasis>virtual</emphasis>
      environment according to how you have configured a virtual
      machine. For example, when the guest attempts to access a hard
      disk, &product-name; redirects these requests to whatever you have
      configured to be the virtual machine's virtual hard disk. This is
      normally an image file on your host.
    </para>

    <para>
      Unfortunately, the x86 platform was never designed to be
      virtualized. Detecting situations in which &product-name; needs to
      take control over the guest code that is executing, as described
      above, is difficult. To achieve this, &product-name; uses
      <emphasis>hardware virtualization</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Intel and AMD processors have support for hardware virtualization.
      This means that these processors can help &product-name; to
      intercept potentially dangerous operations that a guest operating
      system may be attempting and also makes it easier to present
      virtual hardware to a virtual machine.
    </para>

    <para>
      These hardware features differ between Intel and AMD processors.
      Intel named its technology VT-x, AMD calls theirs AMD-V. The Intel
      and AMD support for virtualization is very different in detail,
      but not very different in principle.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        On many systems, the hardware virtualization features first need
        to be enabled in the BIOS before &product-name; can use them.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      Enabling hardware virtualization is <emphasis>required</emphasis>
      in the following scenarios:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Certain rare guest operating systems like OS/2 make use of
          very esoteric processor instructions. For virtual machines
          that are configured to use such an operating system, hardware
          virtualization is enabled automatically.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          &product-name;'s 64-bit guest and multiprocessing (SMP)
          support both require hardware virtualization to be enabled.
          This is not much of a limitation since the vast majority of
          64-bit and multicore CPUs ship with hardware virtualization.
          The exceptions to this rule are some legacy Intel and AMD
          CPUs.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <warning>
      <para>
        Do not run other hypervisors, either open source or commercial
        virtualization products, together with &product-name;. While
        several hypervisors can normally be
        <emphasis>installed</emphasis> in parallel, do not attempt to
        <emphasis>run</emphasis> several virtual machines from competing
        hypervisors at the same time. &product-name; cannot track what
        another hypervisor is currently attempting to do on the same
        host, and especially if several products attempt to use hardware
        virtualization features such as VT-x, this can crash the entire
        host.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
      See <xref linkend="hwvirt-details"/> for a technical discussion of
      hardware virtualization.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="hwvirt-details">

    <title>Details About Hardware Virtualization</title>

    <para>
      With Intel VT-x, there are two distinct modes of CPU operation:
      VMX root mode and non-root mode.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          In root mode, the CPU operates much like older generations of
          processors without VT-x support. There are four privilege
          levels, called rings, and the same instruction set is
          supported, with the addition of several virtualization
          specific instruction. Root mode is what a host operating
          system without virtualization uses, and it is also used by a
          hypervisor when virtualization is active.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          In non-root mode, CPU operation is significantly different.
          There are still four privilege rings and the same instruction
          set, but a new structure called VMCS (Virtual Machine Control
          Structure) now controls the CPU operation and determines how
          certain instructions behave. Non-root mode is where guest
          systems run.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Switching from root mode to non-root mode is called "VM entry",
      the switch back is "VM exit". The VMCS includes a guest and host
      state area which is saved/restored at VM entry and exit. Most
      importantly, the VMCS controls which guest operations will cause
      VM exits.
    </para>

    <para>
      The VMCS provides fairly fine-grained control over what the guests
      can and cannot do. For example, a hypervisor can allow a guest to
      write certain bits in shadowed control registers, but not others.
      This enables efficient virtualization in cases where guests can be
      allowed to write control bits without disrupting the hypervisor,
      while preventing them from altering control bits over which the
      hypervisor needs to retain full control. The VMCS also provides
      control over interrupt delivery and exceptions.
    </para>

    <para>
      Whenever an instruction or event causes a VM exit, the VMCS
      contains information about the exit reason, often with
      accompanying detail. For example, if a write to the CR0 register
      causes an exit, the offending instruction is recorded, along with
      the fact that a write access to a control register caused the
      exit, and information about source and destination register. Thus
      the hypervisor can efficiently handle the condition without
      needing advanced techniques such as CSAM and PATM described above.
    </para>

    <para>
      VT-x inherently avoids several of the problems which software
      virtualization faces. The guest has its own completely separate
      address space not shared with the hypervisor, which eliminates
      potential clashes. Additionally, guest OS kernel code runs at
      privilege ring 0 in VMX non-root mode, obviating the problems by
      running ring 0 code at less privileged levels. For example the
      SYSENTER instruction can transition to ring 0 without causing
      problems. Naturally, even at ring 0 in VMX non-root mode, any I/O
      access by guest code still causes a VM exit, allowing for device
      emulation.
    </para>

    <para>
      The biggest difference between VT-x and AMD-V is that AMD-V
      provides a more complete virtualization environment. VT-x requires
      the VMX non-root code to run with paging enabled, which precludes
      hardware virtualization of real-mode code and non-paged
      protected-mode software. This typically only includes firmware and
      OS loaders, but nevertheless complicates VT-x hypervisor
      implementation. AMD-V does not have this restriction.
    </para>

    <para>
      Of course hardware virtualization is not perfect. Compared to
      software virtualization, the overhead of VM exits is relatively
      high. This causes problems for devices whose emulation requires
      high number of traps. One example is a VGA device in 16-color
      mode, where not only every I/O port access but also every access
      to the framebuffer memory must be trapped.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimproviders">

    <title>Paravirtualization Providers</title>

    <para>
      &product-name; enables the exposure of a paravirtualization
      interface, to facilitate accurate and efficient execution of
      software within a virtual machine. These interfaces require the
      guest operating system to recognize their presence and make use of
      them in order to leverage the benefits of communicating with the
      &product-name; hypervisor.
    </para>

    <para>
      Most modern, mainstream guest operating systems, including Windows
      and Linux, ship with support for one or more paravirtualization
      interfaces. Hence, there is typically no need to install
      additional software in the guest to take advantage of this
      feature.
    </para>

    <para>
      Exposing a paravirtualization provider to the guest operating
      system does not rely on the choice of host platforms. For example,
      the <emphasis>Hyper-V</emphasis> paravirtualization provider can
      be used for VMs to run on any host platform supported by
      &product-name; and not just Windows.
    </para>

    <para>
      &product-name; provides the following interfaces:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Minimal</emphasis>: Announces the
          presence of a virtualized environment. Additionally, reports
          the TSC and APIC frequency to the guest operating system. This
          provider is mandatory for running any Mac OS X guests.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">KVM</emphasis>: Presents a Linux KVM
          hypervisor interface which is recognized by Linux kernels
          version 2.6.25 or later. &product-name;'s implementation
          currently supports paravirtualized clocks and SMP spinlocks.
          This provider is recommended for Linux guests.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Hyper-V</emphasis>: Presents a Microsoft
          Hyper-V hypervisor interface which is recognized by Windows 7
          and newer operating systems. &product-name;'s implementation
          currently supports paravirtualized clocks, APIC frequency
          reporting, guest debugging, guest crash reporting and relaxed
          timer checks. This provider is recommended for Windows guests.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="nestedpaging">

    <title>Nested Paging and VPIDs</title>

    <para>
      In addition to normal hardware virtualization, your processor may
      also support the following additional sophisticated techniques:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Nested paging implements some memory management in hardware,
          which can greatly accelerate hardware virtualization since
          these tasks no longer need to be performed by the
          virtualization software.
        </para>

        <para>
          With nested paging, the hardware provides another level of
          indirection when translating linear to physical addresses.
          Page tables function as before, but linear addresses are now
          translated to "guest physical" addresses first and not
          physical addresses directly. A new set of paging registers now
          exists under the traditional paging mechanism and translates
          from guest physical addresses to host physical addresses,
          which are used to access memory.
        </para>

        <para>
          Nested paging eliminates the overhead caused by VM exits and
          page table accesses. In essence, with nested page tables the
          guest can handle paging without intervention from the
          hypervisor. Nested paging thus significantly improves
          virtualization performance.
        </para>

        <para>
          On AMD processors, nested paging has been available starting
          with the Barcelona (K10) architecture. They now call it rapid
          virtualization indexing (RVI). Intel added support for nested
          paging, which they call extended page tables (EPT), with their
          Core i7 (Nehalem) processors.
        </para>

        <para>
          If nested paging is enabled, the &product-name; hypervisor can
          also use <emphasis>large pages</emphasis> to reduce TLB usage
          and overhead. This can yield a performance improvement of up
          to 5%. To enable this feature for a VM, you use the
          <command>VBoxManage modifyvm --large-pages</command> command.
          See <xref linkend="vboxmanage-modifyvm" />.
        </para>

        <para>
          If you have an Intel CPU with EPT, please consult
          <xref linkend="sec-rec-cve-2018-3646" /> for security concerns
          regarding EPT.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          On Intel CPUs, a hardware feature called Virtual Processor
          Identifiers (VPIDs) can greatly accelerate context switching
          by reducing the need for expensive flushing of the processor's
          Translation Lookaside Buffers (TLBs).
        </para>

        <para>
          To enable these features for a VM, you use the
          <command>VBoxManage modifyvm --vtx-vpid</command> and
          <command>VBoxManage modifyvm --large-pages</command> commands.
          See <xref linkend="vboxmanage-modifyvm" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
